CURRICULUM VITAE

Jacqui Ruesga has almost a decade of experience in international climate change, including under several UN bodies. She is currently New Zealand's lead markets negotiator and Deputy Head of Delegation under the UNFCCC. Last year Jacqui supported Ministerial co-facilitation of Article 6 leading to a consensus outcome. Jacqui has also been co-chair of the Article 6.8 Glasgow Committee on Non-Market Approaches for the last three years. Jacqui manages the International Mitigation team at the Ministry for the Environment, designing and implementing climate policy, including international carbon markets.

EXPERIENCE:

2021-present

Ministry for the Environment

Wellington

MANAGER, INTERNATIONAL CLIMATE MITIGATION (JANUARY 2024-CURRENT)

- Manage team leading the Ministry's international climate change policy and engagement.
- Responsible for the development and delivery of Ministerial and Cabinet advice on New Zealand's climate change commitments under the Paris Agreement.
- Substantial experience working directly with the Minister for Climate Change and his office, including during international negotiations and engagements.
- Significant experience leading complex and politically sensitive policy advice, including through interagency processes, delivering substantial policy including New Zealand's 2035 NDC.
- Strong relationships with leadership teams, and experience developing forward and strategic business planning.

MARKETS NEGOTIATOR, UNFCCC (2021-CURRENT)

- Significant experience in UNFCCC process as Deputy Head of Delegation and lead markets negotiator, as well as Co-chair of the Glasgow Committee on non-market approaches.
- Deep expertise in carbon markets, including Article 6 of the Paris Agreement, voluntary carbon market development, and emission trading schemes.
- Lead New Zealand representative at several international carbon markets organisations, associations, and events such as the Carbon Markets Platform, IETA Climate Summit, Mexico Carbon Forum, among others.
- Establish and maintain key trusted relationships and networks with international counterparts.

MANAGER, CLIMATE STRATEGY (2023)

- Manage team leading the development of substantial and varied climate policies, including the Nationally Determined Contribution Strategy, the Voluntary Carbon Market Framework, and the Second Emissions Reduction Plan (ERP2).
- Substantial experience building and maintaining relationships internally and externally across government, including senior leadership.
- Lead strategic analysis and advice on the role of emissions pricing and the New Zealand Emissions
 Trading Scheme (ETS).
- Extensive experience in the inter-agency coordination process, Ministerial engagement, and full Cabinet process.

SENIOR POLICY ANALYST, INTERNATIONAL CARBON MARKETS (2021-2023)

- Negotiator for Article 6 of the Paris Agreement, representing New Zealand at the UNFCCC and other related international fora including, the OECD, ERCST, IETA, ICAP, APEC, among others.
- Responsible for developing substantive policy analysis and strategic thinking for a new area of New Zealand's climate strategy using international carbon markets towards our Paris Agreement target.

Ottawa

2016-2021 Environment and Climate Change Canada

POLICY ANALYST. MULTILATERAL AFFAIRS DIRECTORATE

- Advance Canada's environmental priorities at key international organizations including the G7/G20, the United Nations, the World Economic Forum (WEF) and the Global Environment Facility (GEF).
- Lead Policy Analyst for Canada's engagement on climate and environment issues at the G20, including Canada's leadership at the Climate Sustainability Working Group (CSWG) and the Environment Senior Officials Meetings, including the negotiation of outcome documents and communiqués.
- Contribute to and support Canada's negotiation process on the Global Pact for the Environment at the United Nations Environment Program in Nairobi, Kenya.
- Communicate and coordinate with partners in international organizations and non-governmental organizations, as well as the private sector in the preparation of international meetings and international travel.
- Develop and maintain networks and relationships with stakeholders including indigenous groups, youth, private sector, non-government organizations, and international organizations for the purpose of consultations and policy development.

EDUCATION:

2014-2016 Norman Paterson School of International Affairs Ottawa

MASTER OF ARTS INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS

SPECIALIZATION IN INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT POLICY

2008-2012 Carleton University

Ottawa

BACHELOR OF ARTS, HIGH HONOURS, POLITICAL SCIENCE

CONCENTRATION INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS

MINOR IN HISTORY

TRAINING

- New People Leaders (2024)
- ASPIRING LEADERS PROGRAMME (2023)
- MEDIA TRAINING (2023)
- Multilateral Negotiations (2018)
- BILATERAL NEGOTIATIONS (2017)

AWARDS:

- ENVIRONMENT AND CLIMATE CHANGE CANADA DEPARTMENTAL AWARD: CITATION OF EXCELLENCE FOR TEAMWORK,
 PARTNERING AND COLLABORATION (2019)
- International Affairs Branch Future Leaders Award (2018)
- Environment and Climate Change Canada Instant Award (2017)
- ENVIRONMENT AND CLIMATE CHANGE CANADA INSTANT AWARD (2016)
- NORMAN PATERSON SCHOOL OF INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS ENTRANCE SCHOLARSHIP (2014)
- CARLETON ACADEMIC SCHOLARSHIP (2011)
- CLARENCE C. GIBSON SCHOLARSHIP (2010)
- R.W.R STEACIE SCHOLARSHIP (2009)
- CARLETON UNIVERSITY ENTRANCE SCHOLARSHIP (2008)